<tool id="halla" name="Halla" version="1.0.0" python_template_version="3.5">
	<description>Hierarchical All-against-All association</description>
    <requirements>
    </requirements>

	<command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        bash '$__tool_directory__/halla_wrapper.sh' '$X' '$Y'  '$m' '$output1' '$output2'  
            ]]></command>

    <inputs>
        <param type="data" name="X"  label="X dataset: A tab-delimited input file, one row per feature, one column per measurement" format="txt"  />
		<param type="data" name="Y"  label="Y dataset: A tab-delimited input file, one row per feature, one column per measurement" format="txt"  />

		<param name="m" type="select" format="text">
					<label>Distance/similarity metric: spearman, pearson, dcor,mi, nmi or xicor</label>
						<option value="spearman">spearman</option>
						<option value="pearson">pearson</option>
						<option value="dcor">dcor</option>	
						<option value="mi">mi</option>	
						<option value="nmi">nmi</option>	
						<option value="xicor">xicor</option>						
		</param>
	
    </inputs>
    
	<outputs>
        	<data name="output1" format="pdf"  />
		 	<data name="output2"  format="zip" label="Halla Output zip results - please download" />
    </outputs>
   <help><![CDATA[
  
  
HAllA (Hierarchical All-against-All association) is a method for finding blocks of associated features in high-dimensional datasets measured from a common set of samples. 
HAllA operates by

* Optionally discretizing mixed continuous and categorical features to a uniform representation

* Hierarchically clustering each dataset separately to generate a pair of data hierarchies

* Performing all-against-all association testing between features across two datasets using robust measures of correlation

* Determining the statistical significance of individual associations by permutation testing

* Iteratively subdividing the space of significant all-against-all correlations into blocks of densely associated occurring as clusters in the original datasets.

.. image:: https://github.com/biobakery/galaxy-upgrade/blob/main/galaxy_halla/fig1.png?raw=true 


 
**Inputs**
==========

HAllA requires as input two tab-delimited text files representing two paired datasets (sets of features) describing the same set of samples


**Outputs**
===========
 
.. image:: https://github.com/biobakery/galaxy-upgrade/blob/main/galaxy_halla/halla_image1.png?raw=true
    :height: 600        
    :width: 600 


**If you use this software, please cite:**
==========================================

Gholamali Rahnavard, Kathleen Sucipto, Lauren J. McIver, Emma Schwager,Jason Lloyd-Price, George Weingart, Yo Sup Moon, Xochitl C. Morgan, Levi Waldron, Eric A. Franzosa, Curtis Huttenhower. High-sensitivity pattern discovery in large multi'omic datasets. (huttenhower.sph.harvard.edu/halla)

    ]]>
</help>
</tool>
