<tool id="mmuphin_adj_batch" name="b.)Adjust batch" version="0.1.0" python_template_version="3.5">
    <requirements>
    </requirements>
    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        bash '$__tool_directory__/mmuphin_wrapper.sh' '$feature_abd' '$batch' '$covariates' '$meta_data' '$output1' '$output2' 
            ]]>
    </command>
    <inputs>
                <param type="data" name="feature_abd"  label="Abundance Table - See format in samples below" format="csv"  />
                <param type="data" name="meta_data"  label="Metadata - See format in samples below" format="csv"  />

		<param name="metadata_headers" type="data"  label="Metadata Headers"  format="mmuphin_metadata_headers" help="Metadata Headers (Output of the first step: Preprocess_Metadata)"/>

 		<param name="batch" type="select" optional="false" multiple="false" label="Batch - For a sample run select StudyID">
                         <options from_dataset="metadata_headers">
                                 <column name="name" index="0"/>
                                <column name="value" index="0"/>
                        </options>
                </param>

		<param name="covariates" type="select" optional="false" multiple="false" label="Covariates - For a sample run select study_condition">
 		         <options from_dataset="metadata_headers">
       				 <column name="name" index="0"/>
        			<column name="value" index="0"/>
    			</options>
    		</param>




    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="output1"  format="csv" label="Adjusted abundance table" />
        <data name="output2"  format="pdf" label="Adjust batch diagnostic" />
    </outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[


**MMUPHin**
===========


MMUPHin is an R package implementing meta-analysis methods for microbial community profiles. It has interfaces for: a) covariate-controlled batch and study effect adjustment, b) meta-analytic differential abundance testing, and meta-analytic discovery of c) discrete (cluster-based) or d) continuous unsupervised population structure.

Overall, MMUPHin enables the normalization and combination of multiple microbial community studies. It can then help in identifying microbes, genes, or pathways that are differential with respect to combined phenotypes. Finally, it can find clusters or gradients of sample types that reproduce consistently among studies.




**Inputs**
==========

**1. Please run the first step: Preprocess_Metadata, using as input the metadata file and use its output in the metadata_headers field**

**2. When you upload the Metadata and Abundance files for this step, make sure you modify the type from Auto-Detect to mmuphin_input**
======================================================================================================================================

As input, MMUPHin requires a properly formatted collection of microbial community studies, with both feature abundances and accompanying metadata. Here we use the five published colorectal cancer (CRC) stool metagenomic studies, incorporated in Thomas et al. (2019). Data for the studies are already conveniently packaged and accessible through the Biocondcutor package curatedMetagenomicData, though additional wranglings are needed to format input for MMUPHin.

Importantly, MMUPHin asks that feature abundances be provided as a feature-by-sample matrix, and the metadata be provided as a data frame. The two objects shoud agree on sample IDs, that is, rowname of the feature abundance matrix and colname of the metadata data frame must agree. Many popular ’omic data classes in R already enforce this standard, such as ExpressionSet from Biobase, or phyloseq from phyloseq.

To minimize users’ efforts in loading data to run the examples, we have properly formatted the five studies for easy access. The feature abundances and metadata can be loaded with the following code chunk. For the interested user, the commented out scripts were used for accessing data directly from curatedMetagenomicData and formatting. It might be worthwhile to read through these as they perform many of the common tasks for preprocessing microbial feature abundance data in R, including sample/feature subsetting, normalization, filtering, etc.

adjust_batch aims to correct for technical study/batch effects in microbial feature abundances. It takes as input the feature-by-sample abundance matrix, and performs batch effect adjustment given provided batch and optional covariate variables. It returns the batch-adjusted abundance matrix. Check help(adjust_batch) for additional details and options. This figure from the paper (figure 2b) shows the desired effect of the batch adjustment: batch effects are removed, making the effect of the biological variable of interest easier to detect.

.. image::  https://github.com/biobakery/galaxy-upgrade/blob/main/mmuphin/adjust_batch.png?raw=true
    :height: 800        
    :width: 600 


As an example we privide two sample files taken from colorectal cancer (CRC) stool metagenomic studies (See links below)

Please download these files to your computer and use the Galaxy Get-Data / Upload file from your computer to upload these two files.




..  _CRC_Feature_Abundances:  https://github.com/biobakery/galaxy-upgrade/blob/main/mmuphin/CRC_abd.csv
..  _CRC_Metadata:  https://github.com/biobakery/galaxy-upgrade/blob/main/mmuphin/CRC_meta.csv


* CRC_Feature_Abundances_ 
* CRC_Metadata_

**Outputs**
===========

In the Galaxy interface we  provide **two** outputs,  a pdf  and a csv 

* Adjust batch diagnostic pdf
* Adjusted abundance table csv


**Documentation**
=================

.. _MMUPHin_General_Documentation:  https://huttenhower.sph.harvard.edu/mmuphin/
.. _MMUPHin_User_Manual:   https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/vignettes/MMUPHin/inst/doc/MMUPHin.html
.. _MMUPHin_Tutorial:  https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/vignettes/MMUPHin/inst/doc/MMUPHin.html
.. _MMUPHin_User_Forum:  https://forum.biobakery.org/

*  MMUPHin_General_Documentation_
*  MMUPHin_User_Manual_
*  MMUPHin_Tutorial_
*  MMUPHin_User_Forum_



**Citation:**
=============


A manuscript describing MMUPHin, with its application in a collection of inflammatory bowel disease studies is currently in preparation:

Siyuan Ma, Dmitry Shungin, Himel Mallick, Melanie Schirmer, Long Nguyen, Raivo Kolde, Eric Franzosa, Hera Vlamakis, Ramnik Xavier, Curtis Huttenhower Population Structure Discovery in Meta-Analyzed Microbial Communities and Inflammatory Bowel Disease.

In the meantime, if you use MMUPHin in your work, please cite the package itself (from within R, enter citation("MMUPHin")):

Ma S (2019). MMUPHin: Meta-analysis Methods with Uniform Pipeline for Heterogeneity in Microbiome Studies. R package version 0.99.3.
 

 
    ]]></help>
</tool>

