<tool id="mmuphin_preprocess_metadata" name="Preprocess Metadata" version="0.1.0" python_template_version="3.5">
    <requirements>
    </requirements>

    <command>
    		python '$__tool_directory__/decode_csv_header.py' '$meta_data' '$output1'</command>
    <inputs>
           <param type="data" name="meta_data"  label="Metadata"  format="csv"  />

    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="output1"  format="mmuphin_metadata_headers" label="Preprocessed metadata (Headers)" />
    </outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[


**MMUPHin**
===========

MMUPHin is an R package implementing meta-analysis methods for microbial community profiles. It has interfaces for: a) covariate-controlled batch and study effect adjustment, b) meta-analytic differential abundance testing, and meta-analytic discovery of c) discrete (cluster-based) or d) continuous unsupervised population structure.

Overall, MMUPHin enables the normalization and combination of multiple microbial community studies. It can then help in identifying microbes, genes, or pathways that are differential with respect to combined phenotypes. Finally, it can find clusters or gradients of sample types that reproduce consistently among studies.

The Galaxy workflow for MMUPHin consists of three steps:

* Read the metadata file and create a headers file to be used in the subsequent steps. For a sample, you can use the CRC_Metadata_sample_ below
* Perform covariate-adjusted batch effect correction
* Perform meta-analytical differential abundance testing


..  _CRC_Metadata_sample:  https://github.com/biobakery/galaxy-upgrade/blob/main/mmuphin/CRC_meta_small.csv

* CRC_Metadata_sample_
 


**Documentation**
=================

.. _MMUPHin_General_Documentation:  https://huttenhower.sph.harvard.edu/mmuphin/
.. _MMUPHin_User_Manual:   https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/vignettes/MMUPHin/inst/doc/MMUPHin.html
.. _MMUPHin_Tutorial:  https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/vignettes/MMUPHin/inst/doc/MMUPHin.html
.. _MMUPHin_User_Forum:  https://forum.biobakery.org/

*  MMUPHin_General_Documentation_
*  MMUPHin_User_Manual_
*  MMUPHin_Tutorial_
*  MMUPHin_User_Forum_



**Citation:**
=============

If you use the  MMUPHin software, please cite our manuscript:

Population Structure Discovery in Meta-Analyzed Microbial Communities and Inflammatory Bowel Disease.

Siyuan Ma, Dmitry Shungin, Himel Mallick, Melanie Schirmer,  View ORCID ProfileLong H. Nguyen, Raivo Kolde, Eric Franzosa, Hera Vlamakis, Ramnik Xavier,   Curtis Huttenhower

https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.08.31.261214v1

 
    ]]></help>
</tool>

